<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>By the King. A proclamation prohibiting the vntimely bringing in of wines, &amp;c.</title>
            <title>Proclamations. 1613-09-11</title>
            <author>England and Wales. Sovereign (1603-1625 : James I)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1613</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 3 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 1 1-bit group-IV TIFF page image.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A22083</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 8489</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S100835</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99836662</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99836662</idno>
            <idno type="VID">946</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A22083)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 946)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1475-1640 ; 1686:04)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>By the King. A proclamation prohibiting the vntimely bringing in of wines, &amp;c.</title>
                  <title>Proclamations. 1613-09-11</title>
                  <author>England and Wales. Sovereign (1603-1625 : James I)</author>
                  <author>James I, King of England, 1566-1625.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 sheet ([1] p.)   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Robert Barker, printer to the Kings most excellent Maiestie,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno Dom. 1613.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dated at end: VVansted the eleuenth day of September, in the eleuenth yeere of our reigne ..</note>
                  <note>Steele notation: That rantly yeere,.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Wine and wine making --  Law and legislation --  Great Britain --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Foreign trade regulation --  Great Britain --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="royal_proclamation">
            <pb facs="tcp:946:1"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 14 -->
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> By the King.</head>
            <head type="sub">
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> A Proclamation prohibiting the vntimely <hi>bringing in of Wines, &amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Oraſmuch as his Maieſtie is informed, That</hi> there is a generall complaint, that the Wines of France, which are brough into this Kingdome, are not, neither haue bene for many yeeres paſt, ſo laſting, nor ſo good and wholeſome for mens bodies, as they were in former times; whereof the chiefe cauſes are appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantly found to be, aſwell in ſome ſome Merchants and others, who (out of greedineſſe of priuate gaine) haue vſed of late yeeres to fetch and bring in thoſe Wines ſooner in the yeere, then in ancient times was vſed or allowed by the Statutes of this Realme: As alſo in the Frenchmen, who doe thereupon for the moſt part uſe to cut their Vines, before the Grapes are fully ripe, And likewiſe doe not ſuffer the Wines to haue their due and true making, before the ſame be bought and ſent into this Realme; His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie therefore to preuent the like inconueniences hereafter, in a commoditie ſo much ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the health of his Subiects, Doeth ſtraitly prohibit and forbid, All and euery per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and perſons whatſoeuer, aſwell being His naturall borne Subiects, as Denizens, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther directly or indirectly, from hence foorth to vnſhip, diſcharge or lay on land, any new Wines of the growth of France, at or in any Port, Hauen, Creeke, or other place within his Highneſſe Realme of England, and Principalitie of Wales, Or to buy or receiue any new Wines of the growth of France, being brought in by any others, vntill the firſt day of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cember now next comming. And ſo vntill the firſt day of December yeerely vpon paine of His Maieſties diſpleaſure, and ſuch penalties, as by the Lawes of this his Maieſties Realme of England, may be inflicted vpon perſons offending againſt His Maieſties Royall commandement. And for the better execution hereof, His Maieſtie doeth further charge and command All Cuſtomers, Comptrollers, and other Officers of His Ports, to whom it ſhall appertaine, And all Fermers of the Cuſtomes and Impoſts, now, and for the time being, their Clerkes and Subſtitutes, That they and euery of them, dot forbeare to take any Entries of ſuch new Wines of the growth of France, that ſhalbe brought into this Realme, by any perſon or perſons whatſoeuer, vntill the ſaid firſt day of December now next comming, and ſo after vntil the firſt day of December yeerely from yeere to yeere, As they and euery of them will anſwere the contrary at their vttermoſt perill.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Giuen at Wanſted <date>the eleuenth day of September, in the eleuenth yeere of Our Reigne of Great Britaine, France, and Ireland.</date>
               </dateline>
               <lb/>
God ſaue the King.</closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>¶ Imprinted at London by Robert Barker, Printer to the Kings moſt Exellent Maieſtie.</p>
            <p>ANNO DOM. 1613.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
